本剧改编自圣经  它们曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
《圣经》前情提要
Previously on the Bible...
耶路撒冷
Jerusalem,
我们的新家园
our new home.
犹太人民 在盟约之地建立了一个王国
The Jewish people have forged a kingdom, in the promised land.
但是他们的生存
But their survival has been
一直在不断的斗争
a constant struggle.
他们被很多大国包围着
Surrounded by great superpowers,
他们一直受到压迫
they have been oppressed,
奴役
enslaved...
和流亡
and exiled.
每一次  都有一个伟大的犹太英雄
Each time, a great Jewish hero
来帮助他们
has come to their aid.
主啊
Lord!
但现在
But now...
他们已屈服于罗马的威力
they've succumbed to the might of Rome.
前进
Forward!
以色列遭受前所未有的灾难
Israel suffers like never before.
人们渴求一个救世主
The people crave a savior,
一个默西亚（救世主）
a Messiah.
《圣经》
在叛乱中的耶路撒冷
Rebellion in Jerusalem.
这边
This way.
一只代表罗马帝国的老鹰
A Roman eagle soars above
悬于新的犹太圣殿之上
the Jews' new Holy Temple.
这对是其信仰的侮辱
An abomination to their faith.
快点
Be quick!
必须把它拆下来
It must be removed.
-有士兵  -逮捕他们
- Guards! - Arrest them!
拦住他们
Hold them off!
快点
Hurry!
带他们走
Bring them!
老鹰是由犹太人的国王
The eagle was put on the Temple
黑落德王放上去的
by the king of the Jews, Herod the Great.
一位由罗马人推上宝座的贵族
A nobleman placed on the throne by the Romans.
再忍一下就好
Just one more.
好了
There...
够了  够了
Enough! Enough!
把你们的脏手拿开
Take your butchering hands off me
不然我就砍了它们
or I will have them removed!
想拆除老鹰的人  过来
Ah, the "bird-men". Come!
认为我对你们的圣殿来说不够干净
My little rebels who think I am not clean enough
不够圣洁  犹太血统
or pure enough, or Jewish enough
不够纯正的叛徒们
for your Holy Temple!
那么我告诉你们  圣殿是我建的
Well, let me tell you something, I built the Holy Temple!
是我建的
I built it!
我要是选择放一只鸟在上面
And if I choose to put a bird on the top
让我的罗马朋友高兴的话  心存感激吧
to keep my Roman friends happy, be grateful!
因为如果你们觉得我难以忍受
Because if you think that I'm hard to live with,
那你们去跟他们接触接触试试
you should try living with them!
出去
Out!
犹太人渴望在自己的领土上获得自由
The Jews long for freedom in their own land.
纳匝肋 加里肋亚
从首都耶路撒冷
From the capital Jerusalem
到贫苦偏僻的加里肋亚
to the provincial backwater of Galilee,
人们靠他们的信仰彼此聊以慰藉
the people take comfort in their faith and each other.
感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
玛丽亚  我的未婚妻
Mary, my betrothed,
你有着我所见过最迷人的双眼
you have the most beautiful eyes I've ever seen,
和最甜美的笑容
and the sweetest smile.
以黑落德王和罗马之名
In the name of Herod and Rome
快缴税
taxes are owed!
-这是在干嘛  -把这个男人带走
- What is this? - We will take this man.
没看出来你们打扰诵经了吗
Can't you see you're interrupting the Scriptures?
-还有你  -不
- And you. - No!
这肯定是个误会
This must be a mistake.
我们在这儿朝拜天主
We're worshipping God here.
你们的天主不关我们的事
Your God, your problem.
若瑟
Joseph!
走吧
Come on!
这是上主的圣地
This is the house of God!
快去你父亲家
Get back to your father's house,
快
be quick.
让开
Get out of my way!
玛丽亚
Mary...
还给我
Give that back!
玛丽亚
Mary...
主与你同在
The Lord is with you.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
很快你将诞下一子
You will soon give birth to a son.
他将会是至高者的儿子
He will be the son of the Most High.
圣神要临于你
The holy spirit will move in you.
不要害怕
Don't be afraid.
我是上主的仆人
I am the Lord's servant.
那要诞生的圣者，将称为天主的儿子
The holy one to be born will be called the Son of God.
玛丽亚
Mary!
Mary?
告诉我发生了什么  玛丽亚  求你
Tell me what's going on, Mary, please!
不能在这
Not here!
你怀孕了
You're pregnant.
你做了什么
What have you done?
你到底都做了什么
What on earth have you done?
没有别人  我发誓
There's been no one, I swear.
肯定有别人  我又不傻
Well, there's been someone, I'm not stupid!
我仍是纯洁之身
I'm still a virgin.
这是上主的作为
This is the work of God.
我不知道为什么会选中我
I don't know why I've been chosen,
但我说的都是实话
but I am telling you the truth.
请你相信我
You must believe me.
我曾以为我了解你
I thought I knew you.
求你了  若瑟
Please, Joseph.
我要你做我丈夫
I need you to be my husband.
我要你做孩子的父亲
I need you to be the father of this child.
他是天主之子
The child of God.
求你  我的爱人  求你相信我
Please, my love, please trust me.
玛丽亚  上主是不会选中我们这种人的
Mary, God doesn't do this to people like us.
主啊  如果这是你的作为
If this be your work, Lord,
请帮帮我吧
please help.
帮帮我们
Help us...
达味之子若瑟
Joseph, son of David,
不要怕
be at peace.
只管娶过你的妻子玛丽亚来
Take Mary as your wife.
她是纯洁的
She is pure.
因为那在她内受生的，是出于圣神
The child she carries is from God.
-荡妇  -无耻  无耻的淫妇
- Jezebel! - Shameless! Shameless whore!
不是我的错  是天主选中了我
It's not my fault, God chose me,
不是我自愿的
I didn't ask for this to happen!
她懂什么
What does she know about anything?
她倒是懂得怎么勾引男人
She knows enough to get pregnant.
-事到如今谁还会娶你  -我会
- Who'll have you now? - I will!
我相信她
I believe her!
我会娶她为妻
And I will take her as my wife.
只要她还愿意嫁我
If she'll still have me.
结婚数月后
Within a few months of marrying,
若瑟和玛丽亚就被迫离开了纳匝肋
Joseph and Mary are forced to leave Nazareth.
玛丽亚  准备好了吗
Mary! Are you ready?
为了更好地控制他们的臣民
To better control their subjects,
罗马开始了大普查
Rome has ordered a census.
所有人都必须返回其出生地
All men must return to the town of their birth.
若瑟带着新婚妻子赶往白冷
Joseph takes his new wife to Bethlehem.
那是一段漫长而又遥远的道路
A hundred miles of treacherous open road,
临盆在即
with a baby due any day.
玛丽亚和若瑟以两人之力与世为敌
Mary and Joseph are alone against the world.
但人们正在朝他们聚拢而来
But others are being drawn towards them.
梅瑟时代曾有一条预言
A prophecy from the time of Moses
断言了犹太民族一个伟大的王的降生
predicts the birth of a great king of the Jews.
天上的异象
Announced in the heavens.
由雅各伯将出现一颗星
A star shall come out of Jacob,
由以色列将兴起一权杖
and a scepter shall rise out of Israel.
坚持住
Hold on!
白冷
要生了  若瑟  要生了
He's coming now! Joseph, he's coming!
坚持住  我去找个落脚地
Hold on, I'm going to find somewhere.
有人吗
Hello?
回来  他要降生了
Stop! He's coming!
能帮帮我们吗
Can anybody help us?
他要降生了  若瑟  现在
He's coming, Joseph, now!
我来了  好吧  来吧
I'm coming! All right, come on!
坚持住
Hold on!
跟紧我
Stay with me!
陛下  占星者巴尔萨扎觐见
Sire, the astrologer, Balthazar.
巴尔萨扎  过来
Balthazar. Come.
喝点酒吗
Wine?
您真是仁慈  陛下
You're very gracious, your majesty.
我宁愿不是如此
I'd rather not.
我很好奇  您对新王都了解些什么
I wonder, what can you tell me of the new king?
-君王  -犹太人的君王
- King? - Of the Jews.
有他的消息吗
What news of him?
犹太人的君王
King of the Jews?
我是不是听错了
Am I missing something?
你来这儿不就是觐见犹太人的君王吗
Did you not come here to see the King of the Jews?
你现在看到的黑落德王
Are you not looking at Herod,
难道不是犹太人的君王吗
King of the Jews?
当然是
Of course.
那还有谁自称为王
Then who is claiming to be king?
现在还没有  他尚未出世
No one. He is not born yet.
这是一个预言  星相昭示了他的降临
It is a prophecy, heralded by the star.
您的经师肯定也收到了启示
Surely your scribes have received the revelation...
星相  预言
Stars? Prophecies?
你打断我进餐就为了这个
You interrupt my meal for this?
如果你不介意的话  回去吧
Now please, if you don't mind...
黑落德王什么也不知道
Herod knows nothing.
跟着星星走
We follow the star.
那个大逆不道的预言出现在哪儿
Where is this traitorous prophecy?
找到了吗
Have you found it?
-在这儿  -读给我听
- Ah, here! - Read it!
"依撒意亚..."
"Isaiah..."
"因此吾主要亲自给你们一个征兆"
"Therefore the Lord himself will give a sign."
看  看那儿
Look, look there!
"有位贞女要怀孕生子"
"A young woman will conceive and give birth to a son."
请帮帮我们
Help us, please!
"他的名字要称为神奇的..."
"He will be called Wonderful..."
玛丽亚  我扶着你
Mary! I've got you.
"谋士..."
"Counselor..."
请帮帮我们
Help us, please.
"强有力的天主..."
"Mighty God..."
"永远之父..."
"Eerlasting Father..."
"和平之王"
"Prince of Peace."
但我才是带来和平的人
But I am the one who brings peace!
你觉得一个孩子能做到吗
Do you think some child could do that?
预言里说没说这个"救世主"
Is it written where this mighty prince
将在哪里降生
will be born?
米该亚说他将出生在白冷
Micah says it will be Bethlehem.
白冷  集合部队
Bethlehem! Gather the troops!
我们的儿子...
Our son...
感谢天主
Thanks be to God.
夫人
Lady,
我相信您的儿子必是其子民未来的君王
I believe your son is the promised king of his people.
他叫什么名字
What is his name?
耶稣
Jesus.
他的名字是耶稣
His name is Jesus.
玛丽亚
Mary!
我们得走了  马上出发
We have to leave. Now.
我也没法解释  相信我就好
I can't explain, just trust me.
当黑落德王听说有一位新的王在白冷诞生
When Herod hears a new king is being born in Bethlehem
他便下令杀死所有婴儿
He orders the murder of every infant boy.
把你们找到的婴儿都杀死
Kill any you find!
这边
This way!
-都抓起来  -我的儿子
- Get them all!  - My son!
抢下那个男孩
Get the boy!
这是对无辜平民的屠杀
The massacre of the innocents.
只有一个孩子免于此难
One child escapes.
黑落德王永远不会知道  在白冷的屠杀
Herod will never know that the slaughter in Bethlehem
其实是徒劳无功
was for nothing.
他也行将就木
He's dying.
他的最后一个偏执举动
His last paranoid act
就是以谋反的罪名处死了自己的长子
the execution of his eldest son for plotting against him.
父亲  求你了
Father, please!
黑落德死后
When Herod dies,
人民看到了重获自由的希望
the people sense an opportunity to win their freedom.
以色列人爆发了
Israel explodes.
但罗马人也没有手软
But the Roman response is brutal.
叛乱被残酷地镇压了
The uprising is crushed.
仅加里肋亚地区  就有两千人被钉十字架
In Galilee alone two thousand are crucified.
加里肋亚
耶稣和他的家人从埃及返回
Jesus and his family return from Egypt.
我们就快到了  耶稣  马上就到家了
We're nearly there, Jesus. We're almost home.
一个十年的黑暗已经笼罩着以色列
A decade of darkness has fallen over Israel.
若瑟
Joseph!
他们有何过错
What have they done?
我们要相信天主自有安排
We must trust in God's plan.
一如他信任我们
As he trusts in us.
二十五年后
罗马帝国直接控制了耶路撒冷和犹太地区
Rome has taken direct control of Jerusalem and Judea.
黑落德的儿子阿尔赫劳正在等待着
Herod's son Antipas awaits the arrival
二十年来罗马的第四任总督来临
of the fourth Roman governor in twenty years,
傲慢残忍的般雀·比拉多总督
the arrogant and ruthless Pontius Pilate.
欢迎  总督
Greetings, Prefect.
欢迎来到犹太
Welcome to Judea.
希望您能在这里拥有一份充实平和的生活
I hope your time here will be prosperous and peaceful.
我也正打算确保我的生活能如此
I intend to make sure it is.
凯撒的命令  异教活动必须停止
Orders from Caesar. This dissent must stop.
对于比拉多和阿尔赫劳来说
For Pilate and Antipas,
任何群众集会都具有威胁性
any gathering of people is a threat.
悔改吧  你的罪将会得到宽恕
Repent and your sins shall be forgiven.
在约旦河岸
At the river Jordan,
人们络绎不绝地来找洗者若翰
crowds flock to John the Baptist.
我为你们施洗  准备迎接新的国度吧
I baptize you, ready for the new kingdom.
你已洁净
As you are cleansed...
所有以色列人也将和你一样洁净
... so all Israel shall be cleansed!
-你说有麻烦  -在沙漠地带
- You said there was trouble. - In the desert.
人们都成群结队去找那个野人似的若翰
The people are flocking to this wild man, John.
他们认为他是先知
They think he's a prophet.
甚至有人认为他就是默西亚
Some even call him the 'Messiah'.
（默西亚 指傅油者 即预言中的耶稣 犹太人所期待的王)
你当真悔改了吗
Do you truly repent?
上主的斧子已经放在树根上了
God's axe is ready.
凡不结好果子的树
Every tree that does not produce good fruit
必将砍倒 投入火中 （玛窦福音3：:10）
will be cut down and thrown into the fire.
凡有血肉的都要看见天主的救援
All flesh shall see the salvation of God!
默西亚又是什么
And what is a Messiah?
是犹太人的救世主
The redeemer of the Jews.
上主的受傅者 来拯救他们
Anointed by God to set them free.
那你可得好好留心这位默西亚了
Then you need to keep an eye on your 'Messiah'.
即将到来的那一位  大过我
There is one to come, greater than me,
他将用圣神与火来施洗
who will baptize with fire.
我不过是旷野中的声音
I am just the voice in the wilderness,
预备上主的...
preparing the way for the...
...道路
...Lord.
继续
Don't stop.
我应该受你的洗啊
Surely I need you to baptize me.
若翰  因为我们应当这样 以完成全义
John, what you are doing is right.
你暂且容许吧
Baptize me.
受洗后  耶稣被圣神领往旷野
After his baptism, Jesus enters the wilderness.
在旷野中的四十天  他的灵魂饱受考验
For forty days his spirit is tested,
为他之后将要面临的挑战做准备
preparing him for the challenges to come.
撒殚
Satan...
你若是  天主子
If you are the 'Son of God',
就命这些石头变成饼吧
command that this stone becomes bread.
人生活不只靠饼
Man shall not live by bread alone,
而也靠天主口中所发的一切言语
but on every word that comes from the mouth of God.
你若是天主子  就跳下去
If God loves you, throw yourself down.
他为你吩咐了自己的天使 他们要用手托着你
His angels will lift you up in their hands.
你不可试探上主 你的天主
How dare you put God to the test!
你若俯伏朝拜我
If you will bow down and worship me,
我必把这一切交给你
I will give you the whole world.
钉死他
Crucify him!
去吧 撒殚
Get away from me, Satan.
我朝拜上主
I worship the Lord,
我的天主
my God.
惟独事奉他
and serve him only!
耶稣抵挡住了撒殚的诱惑
Jesus resists Satan's temptations
并准备开始完成他的使命
and prepares to begin his mission.
但洗者若翰无法与他同行
But it will be without John the Baptist.
他被阿尔赫劳所抓
He has been arrested by Antipas.
快点  你这贱民
Come on, scum!
进去
Get in!
加里肋亚海
需要帮忙吗
Do you need help?
我不是在寻求帮助
I'm not looking for any help.
更何况  也没什么可帮的
And besides, there's nothing to help with.
你在干什么
Hey, what are you doing?
你不能就这么爬上我的船
You can't just climb into my boat!
没错  你说得对  请助我一臂之力吧
Yeah, you're right. Give me a helping hand.
你这是干什么呢
What do you think you're doing?
我们要去捕鱼
We're going fishing.
大白天的  没有鱼可捕
There are no fish out there this time of day.
其实  什么时候都捕不到鱼
In fact, there are no fish out there any time of day.
伯多禄
Peter...
给我一小时的时间
just give me an hour,
我将给你一个全新的生活
and I will give you a whole new life.
谁说我想要什么新生活了
Who says I want one?
都跟你说了
I tell you,
现在没有鱼可捕
there's no fish out there.
我该怎么处置你呢
What am I going to do with you?
你  还有你那张危险的嘴
You and your dangerous mouth.
静静聆听
Listen.
听一个煽动暴乱的傻瓜吗  算了吧
To a seditious fool? I don't think so.
听上主的旨意
To God's message.
'天国近了'
'The Kingdom of Heaven is near.'
这么说  你承认自己是默西亚了
So you do claim to be the Messiah?
不
No.
但你认为他要来了
But you think he's coming.
不
No.
他已经来了
He's already here.
就在这里
He's here.
在外面
Out there.
传播上主的真理
Speaking God's truth,
开启人的心智
opening the hearts of all men.
这是怎么回事
How did this happen?
你做了什么
What did you do?
我在给你改变人生的机会
I'm giving you the chance to change your life.
伯多禄  来跟从我
Peter, come with me.
别再捕鱼了  我要叫你成为渔人的渔夫
Give up catching fish and I will make you a fisher of men.
我们要做什么
What are we going to do?
改变世界
Change the world.
他将带来正义与公平的新时代
He will bring a new age of righteousness and justice!
他的力量将带领人类迈向新世界
His power will draw all men to a new world!
全人类
All people!
下集《圣经》预告
Next time on the Bible...
玛丽亚  他回来了
Mary! He's here!
谁
Who?
耶稣  他回来了
Jesus! He's back.
我听说了一个年轻先知
I've had reports of a young prophet,
纳匝肋人耶稣
a Jesus of Nazareth.
他在加里肋亚有一大批追随者
He has a big following in Galilee.
传闻说他会来耶路撒冷
It's rumored he'll come to Jerusalem.
他能创造奇迹
He works miracles.
都这么吹
They all do.
神贫的人是有福的  因为天国是他们的
Blessed are the poor, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
温良的人是有福的  因为他们要承受地土
Blessed are the meek, for they shall inherit the earth.
你说什么
What are you saying?
你说你就是被上主选中
That you are the Messiah,
派来人间的默西亚吗
the chosen one sent by God?
不可能
No!
预言开始应验了
It has begun.
有五千人前往见他
Five thousand came to see him.
五千人
Five thousand.
有人说那个耶稣把一个死人救活了
They say this Jesus has raised a man from the dead.
信从我的将永远不会死亡
Whoever believes in me shall never die.
你会为此付出代价
You'll pay the price for this!
正如你的朋友洗者若翰一样
Like your friend John the Baptist!
过些日子我们就去耶路撒冷
Soon we go to Jerusalem.
这样太危险
It's too dangerous.
耶稣从加里肋亚来耶路撒冷过逾越节
The Messiah from Galilee in Jerusalem at Passover.
真是时候
How timely.
如果他与万千拥护者相伴而来
What if he comes with thousands of supporters,
随着庆祝节日的人们相继到来
the city will already be breaking at the seams
这城将会人满为患
with those arriving for the festival.
犹太人的王
King of the Jews!
你可以如军队般带领我们
You can lead us like an army.
我们有能力击败罗马人
We are strong enough to beat the Romans!
不  不应该通过这种方式
No, this is not the way.
罗马渣滓  罗马强盗  要他们好看
Roman scum! Roman thieves! Let's show them!
罗马强盗
Roman thieves!
他们希望你做他们的王
They want you to be their king.
我们必须阻止这个神棍
We must not allow this miracle man,
这个骗子  来破坏逾越节
this fraud, to disrupt Passover.
倘若你饥渴慕义
If you hunger for righteousness,
你必经过我才感受得到
you will be filled... through me.
这事比拉多知道吗
Does Pilate know?
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!